Guide to the Paul Weinberg Photographs, 1979-2007 RL.01358
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Paul Weinberg photographs
1979-2007
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Weinberg, Paul
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
RL.01358
15 Linear Feet 24 boxes; 10 CD-Rs; 1 oversize folder
South African born documentary photographer. Collection contains over 400 black-and-white and color prints from several of Weinberg's exhibits and books on Southern Africa and other regions. Titles of projects include: Travelling Light; The Moving Spirit; In Search of the San; Going Home; Once We Were Hunters; Kosi Bay; Working the Land & Back to the Land; and Durban: Impressions of an African City. The photographs document rural indigenous communities and urban culture in several African countries; events photographed include religious celebrations and rituals, a poetry festival, and South Africa's first democratic elections (1994). Also included high-resolution scans of photographs in the collection. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
434 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Access to electronic files is only available onsite.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Paul Weinberg photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006.
Biographical Note
Paul Weinberg is a South African-born documentary photographer, filmmaker, writer, curator, educator, and archivist. He began his career in the early 1980s by working for South African NGOs, and photographing current events for news agencies and foreign newspapers.
He was a founding member of Afrapix and South, the collective photo agencies that gained local and international recognition for their uncompromising role in documenting apartheid, and popular resistance to it. From 1990 onwards he increasingly concentrated on feature rather than news photography.
His documentary work has been widely exhibited and published. In addition, he has served as the curator, coordinator, and mentor for many photographic projects involving the work of other South African photographers.
Collection Overview
South African-born documentary photographer. Collection contains over 400 black-and-white and color prints, printed in both darkroom and digital formats, from several of Weinberg's exhibits and books on Southern Africa and other regions. Titles of projects include: Travelling Light; The Moving Spirit; In Search of the San; Going Home; Once We Were Hunters; Kosi Bay; Working the Land & Back to the Land; and Durban: Impressions of an African City.
The photographs document rural indigenous communities and urban culture in several African countries; events photographed include religious celebrations and rituals, a poetry festival and South Africa's first democratic elections (1994).
Also included is an oversize publicity poster for the "Moving Spirit" project, and high-resolution scans of the photographs in the collection; the CD-ROMs have been separated from teh collection and their contents mounted on the library server.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Africa, East -- Social life and customs; Africa, Southern -- Religious life and customs -- Pictorial works; Africa, Southern -- Social life and customs; Documentary photography -- Africa, East; Documentary photography -- South Africa; Elections -- South Africa; Photographers -- South Africa; San (African people) -- Social conditions; San (African people) -- Pictorial works; South Africa -- Pictorial works; Black-and-white photographs; CD-ROMs; Color photographs; Digital prints; Gelatin silver prints; Inkjet prints; Weinberg, Paul; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- Accession (2006-0119), 1979-2007
  Scope and Contents note
  Accession contains black-and-white and color prints from photographer Paul Weinberg's exhibits and books on Southern African peoples, cultures, social conditions, and landscapes. Titles of projects and books in this collection: Travelling Light; The Moving Spirit; In Search of the San; Going Home; Once We Were Hunters; Kosi Bay; Working the Land & Back to the Land; and Durban-Impressions of an African City. Photographs document rural indigenous communities and urban culture in several African countries. There is also an oversize color exhibit poster related to the "Moving Spirit" project.
  Also included are 10 CD-ROMs containing high-resolution scans of photographs in the collection. These disks have been removed from the collection and migrated to the library's electronic records server.
  - Photographic Prints, 24 boxes
    - Travelling Light, 1979-2004, Special Edition, 17x22 inches, 13 b/w digital prints on Hahnemuhle Inkjet Fine Art Paper (640267-501 Photo Rag 308 gm2) (Box 1)
      A 25 year retrospective of Paul's photography in Southern Africa.
    - Travelling Light, Special Edition, 17x22, 13 b/w digital prints (Box 2)
    - Travelling Light, Special Edition, 17x22, 13 b/w digital prints (Box 3)
    - Travelling Light, Special Edition, 17x22, 13 b/w digital prints (Box 4)
    - Travelling Light, Special Edition, 17x22, 13 b/w digital prints (Box 5)
    - Travelling Light, Special Edition, 17x22, 13 b/w digital prints (Box 6)
    - Travelling Light, Special Edition, 17x22, 14 b/w digital prints) (Box 7)
    - The Moving Spirit, 16 ½ x 23 ½ inches, 18 b/w digital prints (Box 8)
      Photographs of religious rituals and spiritual practices in Africa.
    - The Moving Spirit, 16 ½ x 23 ½ inches, 18 b/w digital prints (Box 9)
    - The Moving Spirit, 16 ½ x 23 ½ inches, 20 b/w digital prints (Box 10)
    - The Moving Spirit, color exhibition poster, 2007, 33 1/8 x 23 3/8 inches (Oversize-folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Entitled "Moving Spirit: Spirituality in Southern Africa," this poster publicized the exhibit held from June through September, 2007, at the South African Jewish Museum, Cape Town. The black-and-white Weinberg photograph used on the poster shows a man in religious robes standing in a body of water, and is titled "At prayer, Zion Church sect, Inhaca Island, Mozambique."
    - In Search of the San, 1984-1997, 12x16 inches, 22 b/w silver prints (Box 11)
      Photographs of Africa's first people, the San.
    - In Search of the San, 1984-1997, 8x10, 20 b/w silver prints (Box 12)
    - Going Home, 1984-1989, 8x10 inches, 8 ¾ x 12 7/8 inches, 18 b/w silver prints (Box 13)
      Photographs of Pietermaritzburg, the neighborhood where Weinberg was raised
    - Going Home, 1984-1989, 8x10, 8 ¾ x 12 7/8, 16 b/w silver prints (Box 14)
    - Going Home, 1984-1989, 8x10, 8 ¾ x 12 7/8, 17 b/w silver prints (Box 15)
    - Once We Were Hunters, 1999, 10x15 inches, 21 digital color prints (Box 16)
      Photo and textual documentation of seven indigenous groups and their relationship to the land.
    - Once We Were Hunters, 1999, 10x15, 21 digital color prints (Box 17)
    - The Culture of Cricket, 2002 October-December, 12x16 inches, 10 b/w silver prints (Box 18)
      Depicts the culture of cricket in South Africa, urban to rural.
    - Khekhekhe Mtetwa: The story of a Zulu Family, 2000-2002, 12x16 inches, 17 b/w silver prints. (Box 18)
      Photographs of Khekhekhe Mtetwa, a famous sangoma (traditional healer) in Kwa Zulu Natal.
    - Kosi Bay, 1987-1995, 10 ½ x 15 ¼, 11 ½ x 15, and 12x16 inches, 20 b/w silver prints (Box 19)
      Images are of a community of fishermen located on the Mozambique border of Kwa Zulu Natal. This project received the Mother Jones Documentary Award in 1983.
    - Kosi Bay, 1993, 10 ½ x15 ¼, 11 ½ x15, 12x16, 10 b/w silver prints (Box 20)
    - Working the Land & Back to the Land, 1980s, 12 x 15 ¾ inches, 10 b/w silver prints (Box 20)
      Weinberg took these photographs while working at the Environmental and Development Agency (EDA) as photographer and picture editor.
    - Working the Land & Back to the Land, 1980s, 12x15 ¾, 10 b/w silver prints (Box 21)
    - Durban: Impressions of an African City, 1995-2002, 10 x 14 ¼ inches, 16 digital color prints (Box 22)
    - Durban: Impressions of an African City, 1995-2002, 10 x 14 ¼ inches, 17 digital color prints (Box 23)
    - An End to Waiting, 1994, 11 ¾ x 16 ½ inches, 20 b/w digital prints (Box 24)
      Signed special edition. These photographs were taken during the first South African democratic election from February to May, 1994.
    - Poetry Africa, 2003 April, 12x16 inches, 10 b/w silver prints (Box 24)
      Photographs were taken at the annual Poetry Africa festival in Durban, South Africa.
  - Electronic Files, 10 cdrs
    - In Search of the San (Data-cd 1)
    - Travelling Light (Data-cd 1)
    - Once We Were Hunters - Mozambique and Namibia (Data-cd 2)
    - Once We Were Hunters - Bushmen - Namibia (Data-cd 3)
    - Once We Were Hunters - Kenya and Maputuland (Data-cd 4)
    - Once We Were Hunters - Kenya (Data-cd 5)
    - Once We Were Hunters - Zimbabwe and Richtersveld (Data-cd 6)
    - Impressions of an African City (Data-cd 7)
    - Elections (Data-cd 8)
    - The Moving Spirit - Part One (Data-cd 9)
    - The Moving Spirit - Part Two (Data-cd 10)